# **Ibad Ur Rahman**

#### DATA SCIENTIST

9 Bellefield Street, S3-7PQ, Sheffield, United Kingdom

□ (+44) 78-9414-6461 | Sibad2762@gmail.com | Aibadia.github.io | Dibadia | Dibad2762

# Summary.

I have strong mathematical knowledge of Machine learning Algorithms along with proficient programming skills and good team working skills. Have worked on Deep Learning and Attention Mechanisms, have also worked on Bayesian Approach to Machine Learning. Currently working at Barclays UK as a Data Scientist. Occasionally I write articles on medium explaining the concepts of Data Science in simplistic way. I like to understand machine learning algorithms from a Probabilistic or (Bayesian) perspective.

## Education

#### The University of Sheffield

Sheffield, United Kingdom

MSc in Data Analytics

Sept. 2018 - Sept. 2019

- Text Processing, Machine Learning and Adaptive Intelligence (in Python), Statistical Data Science in R, Industrial Team Project, Natural Language Processing, Scalable Machine Learning, Professional Issues, Parallel Computing with GPU, Individual dissertation project
- · Acheived overall Distinction in First Semester.
- Dissertation Topic: Interpretable Probabilistic Deep Learning for Text Classification which includes applying bayesian modeling on Deep Recurrent Neural Networks to make the model better explainable.

#### FAST(National University of Computer and Emerging Sciences)

Karachi, Pakistan

**BACHELORS IN COMPUTER SCIENCE** 

Aug. 2014 - May. 2018

Main courses include: Software Engineering, Data Science, Object Oriented Programming, Algorithms, Data Structures, Introduction to Operating Systems, Computer Networks, Introduction to Programming, Discrete Structures, Database Design, Information Processing Techniques

## Skills\_\_\_\_\_

**Data Science** NLP,Bayesian Neural Networks, Bayesian Approach to Regression, Predictive Modeling

Productionising Model, Machine Learning from a Probabilistic Perspective, Model Optimization

**Deep Learning Libraries** pytorch, tensorflow, keras, scikit-learn

**Data Pre-processing / Visualization Libraries** NLTK, pandas, numpy, seaborn, plotly, folium(for geospatial visualization)

Big-Data Elastic Stack (ELK), pyspark

**Programming** Python(Expert),R,C(proficient),SQL,MySQL,C#,LaTeX,Django,MVC, .NET

**Cloud** Amazon Web Services,Google Colab, Google BigQuery

# **Experience**

#### **Data Scientist**

Barclays UK September. 2020 - Present

• Currently working on the productionising of the Customer Recommendation System model at Barclays, My responsibilities also include making the code scalable, creating architecture for automated machine learning model deployement

#### **Big Data Science Engineer (Elastic Stack)**

BARCLAYS UK

October. 2019 - September. 2020

 Working with logs coming from different sources, creating ingestion pipelines. Writing alerts on Kibana to make sure any unusual event is notified

#### **Data Engineer**

NexDegree

Jun. 2018 - September. 2018

- Data-Pipeline and deployment of a Machine Learning Model for a micro-finance bank which gives out loan based on the User Behaviour.
- · Geo-Visualisation for a bank to get the better idea of which location gives the highest return of loan.
- · Natural Language Processing, Clustering Analysis for an online pharmacy to extract business insights and general user behaviour.
- Explaining the model results to the client and suggesting business benefits the organization can get using Machine Learning.

# **Projects**.

#### **Interpretable Probabilistic Deep Learning for Text Classification**

THE UNIVERSITY OF SHEFFIELD June. 2019 - September. 2019

Applied Variational Inference and MCDropout approach on Encoder Decoder Architecture in order to make the model for text classification
more interpretable. Applied Bayesian Machine learning techniques on RNN along with Attention Mechanism to make it predict the sentiment
of a text much better with explanation given by the model of its prediction. This can be also be applied to healthcare related machine learning
as there is a dire need of explanation for a prediction done by the model. This techniques does not depends completely on the model but
rather gives a measure of confidence and also highlights the parts of the input that were responsible for the particular prediction.

#### Validation of Scoring Criteria and Scoring Thresholds within GWEEK's Speech Intelligence

**GWEEK'S SPEECH INTELLIGENCE** 

Feb. 2019 - May. 2019

Objectives of this project were identifying the existence of any relationship between GWEEK score and Vocabulary, and classifying between
Read and Planned Speech. As a result of the first task, it was found that Vocabulary did not have a major impact on the GWEEK score. For
second task, Deep Learning, as well as classical Machine Learning approaches were applied on raw audio data and extracted text data from the
audio. The classical machine learning methods on extracted text fetched better results than the Deep Learning approach on raw audio, which
implies that extracted features given to model work better than raw features like audio.

#### **Detailed Analysis of Bitcoins Transactions using Big-Query**

Detailed and his of 001CD of his in transactions data annible on Karala through Consola Dis Ourse.

- Detailed analysis of 821GB of bitcoin transactions data available on Kaggle through Google Big Query.
- Analysed the trends in transactions and some of its unique characteristics using plotly, Google BigQuery api, and python notebook.
- Link to analysis: https://www.kaggle.com/ibadia/bitcoin-101-bitcoins-and-detailed-insights.

#### **Nex Generation Panel**

BACHELORS FINAL YEAR PROJECT

Aug. 2017 - May. 2018

Feb. 2018 - March. 2018

- A web interface with Hadoop distributed framework on backend to analyze big data of different types.
- · Can process any amount of data of different types or of any domain and give analytics.
- Can perform data segmentation using generic code for any data
- Tools Used: Python, javascript, d3.js, hadoop, HDFS

# **Publications**

### Artificial Neural Networks explained with code without matrices

Меріим

KAGGLE

Jan. 2018

Article published on Medium explaining the basics of neural networks with code. Link to article: https://medium.com/@ibaad/neural-networks-code-without-matrix-ee55e5e9bbde

#### Linear Regression: A Maximum Likelihood Approach

GOOD AUDIENCE

Jan. 2018

 Article published on Good Audience Magazine through Medium explaining how Linear Regression can be viewed using a Maximum Likelihood Approach instead of the naive approach.

#### **Bitcoin 101: How transaction works in Bitcoin**

ALTCOIN MAGAZINE

Jan. 2018

 Article published on ALTCOIN MAGAZINE through medium discussing how basic bitcoin transactions work in simplistic way for people with less technical knowledge of Blockchain.

# **Program Committees**

- 2018 **Secretary**, Data Science Society, University of Sheffield
- 2017 Teaching Assistant -Big Data, NEDUET
- 2016 **Head**, Gaditek Dockers Challenge(DevDay 2016)
- 2015 Member, Speed Programming Competition (Procom 2015)
- 2014 Member, Speed Programming Competition (Procom 2014)

## **Honors & Awards**

- 2019 Mentioned for Industrial work at the University website, University of Sheffield
- 2018 Winner, Speed Programming Competition, IBA Probattle
- 2018 **Runner Up,** Speed Programming (DEVELOPERS DAY)
- 2016 Winner, Programming Competition, (CODERS CUP) by ACM
- 2015 Winner, CBM Programming Competition
- 2015 Winner, FAST INTRAMUN (Debating)